#### Ahmed S Ali

## **Machine Learning Engineer and Cloud Developer**

Goal oriented Machine Learning Engineer with creative solutions and lateral thinking. Experienced in developing full-stack applications using modern tools and processes. Skilled in implementing Machine Learning algorithms to drive business value. Able to learn new technologies and apply them using principles and methodologies.

(647) 564-5656

ahmedshahrukhali@gmail.com

## **Experience**

## **Sharpest Minds**

Fellowship — Full Stack ML Application

**Technology:** Python, React, AWS, Flask, Spacy, NLTK, DynamoDB (NoSQL?) TBC Intelligent Applicant - Design a new experience for Job-seekers

- Manipulated unstructured textual data from job boards to build an intelligent and interactive application for applicants to help applicants get job-ready
- Developed a Natural Language Processing (NLP) model to extract key information like required Skills & Experience from job descriptions.
- Deployed the application and expanded the pipeline using AWS to increase efficiency and automation add MLOps to employ Continuous Improvement / retraining clustering algorithm
- Designed an intuitive user interface focused on ease of use, and comprehensive results?
- Used clustering algorithms to understand the overlap of skills within and across domains
- Created a recommender system to provide tailored advice using users' existing skills (extended use case)
- Used information from real roles/companies to help users understand the career path resumes.indeed.com (extended)

# Hong Kong University of Science and Technology Specialization — Full Stack Web Development with Angular

Technology: Angular, Node.js, npm, Bootstrap, ExpressServer, Postman, mongoDB?

 Built unique webpages with client-side JavaScript frameworks and the Angular framework to implement a functional front-end web application using Angular.

- Created single page applications in Angular using various features including directives, components, and services.
- Used Angular Material, Angular Flex-Layout, Observables and RxJS for designing responsive Angular applications.
- Made use of server-side concepts, such as CRUD and REST using NoSQL database in MongoDB and communication over JSON and XML.
- Configured backend servers using NodeJS framework Express.js.
- Built a RESTful API for the front-end to access backend services and setup Local & OAuth authentication, and HTTPS security.

### **IBM**

#### **Professional Certificate - Data Scientist**

- Made RESTful API calls to the Foursquare API to retrieve data about venues in different neighborhoods around the world.
- Creatively addressed situations where data was not readily available by scraping web data and parsing HTML code.
- Utilized Python and its pandas library to manipulate data to refine skills for exploring and analyzing data.
- Used the Folium library to generate maps of geospatial data and to visually communicate results and findings.

## Coursera — Modeling Data Warehouses using Apache Hive

Created a data warehouse by using a star schema modeling technique Built tables in the database using Apache Hadoop and Apache Hive.

#### **EDUCATION**

Carleton University, Ottawa — Bachelor of Electrical Engineering
JAN 2013 - JUL 2017

#### **EXPERIENCE**

**RBC, Toronto** — Advisor, Banking NOV 2020 - PRESENT

Provided client-focused sales expertise and natural problem-solving skills to maximize each client interaction.

Helped clients with their banking, credit, and investment needs.

## RBC, Toronto — Advisor, Travel

#### MAR 2020 - OCT 2020

Demonstrated flexibility, eagerness to learn, strong personal ethics, and a hunger for success.

Problem-solving and people skills, with the ability to build strong relationships and proactively connect with clients.

## RBW Payments, Dubai - Account Manager

#### **JAN 2018 - JAN 2020**

Managed the inclusion of a 'Loyalty Rewards Program' to improve customer experience, while also offering partners more consumer data insight and increasing partner revenue by over 15%.

Developed customer relationships with more than 100 local businesses across all industries in 2 years.

#### **TOOLS**

Microsoft Excel

**Python Programming** 

SQL

Scikit-Learn

Natural Language Toolkit (NLTK)

NoSQL databases
APIs
Apache Hadoop
Map/Reduce
Apache Spark
Splunk
HQL
Pentaho
SKILLS
Exploratory Data Analysis
Exploratory Data Analysis  Data Visualization
Data Visualization
Data Visualization Predictive Modeling
Data Visualization  Predictive Modeling  Data Validation
Data Visualization  Predictive Modeling  Data Validation  Data Wrangling and Preparation
Data Visualization Predictive Modeling Data Validation Data Wrangling and Preparation Data Warehouse
Data Visualization Predictive Modeling Data Validation Data Wrangling and Preparation Data Warehouse Database (DB) Design
Data Visualization  Predictive Modeling  Data Validation  Data Wrangling and Preparation  Data Warehouse  Database (DB) Design  Entity-Relationship (E-R) Model
Data Visualization Predictive Modeling Data Validation Data Wrangling and Preparation Data Warehouse Database (DB) Design Entity-Relationship (E-R) Model Database (DBMS)

**Data Warehousing** 

Materialized View

Business Intelligence

Machine Learning (ML)

Algorithms

Time Series Analysis

Sentiment Analysis